Finding Aid for United Church of Christ. United Northern Association (Mich.) records, 1889-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United Church of Christ. United Northern Association (Mich.) records 1889-1989
United Church of Christ. United Northern Association (Mich.)
2 linear feet
89346 Ba 2
Association formed from the merger of the Grand Traverse, Lake Superior, and Cheboygan associations of the Congregational Church (later the United Church of Christ). Administrative records of the association and of the associations from which it was formed.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the Association (donor no. 7252 ) in multiple accessions beginning in September 1985.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
The formal history of the United Church of Christ in Michigan begins on October 11, 1842 when the Congregational churches were first organized into a state conference. Some area associations, formed through the grouping of local churches, developed later. The first, the Grand Traverse Association, was formed in 1862 and existed with weakly defined boundaries until the 1870s, when the Lake Superior and Cheboygan Associations were created.
Each of these Associations existed independently for a century. In June 1976, the Michigan Conference initiated a three year program, designed to regroup existing regional associations into four larger associations. They are the Eastern Association, Central Association, Western Association, and Northern Association.
The formation of the United Northern Association was accomplished through the Steering Committee, established by representatives of the Grand Traverse, Lake Superior, and Cheboygan Associations to oversee the organization. Efforts were successful, and the United Northern Association met for the first time on October 8-9, 1977.
This record group contains both the records of the Grand Traverse, Lake Superior, and Cheboygan Associations prior to restructuring, and the records of efforts leading to the formation of the United Northern Association. Despite the absence of the early records of the Grand Traverse and Cheboygan Associations, this record group documents attitudes concerning the denominations which fused to form the United Church of Christ, as well as the organizational restructuring which occurred in the late 1970s.
The records of the Northern Association of the United Church of Christ are divided into five series: Michigan Conference, United Northern Association, Grand Traverse Association, Lake Superior Association, and Cheboygan Association.
Subjects:
United Church of Christ. Michigan Conference.; United Church of Christ. Cheboygan Association (Mich.); United Church of Christ. Grand Traverse Association (Mich.); United Church of Christ. Lake Superior Association (Mich.)
- Michigan Conference
  The Michigan Conference conference includes materials of the Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ which relate to the United Northern Association or are important to the understanding of the organization of the church. Included here is the constitution of the Michigan Conference, a copy of the Restructure Proposal implemented on the state level between 1976 and 1979, and papers concerning the Olivet committee, which was concerned with church affiliated colleges.
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Restructure Proposal 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Olivet Committee 1964 (Box 1)
- United Northern Association
  The United Northern Association series contains by-laws, files documenting the formation of the Northern Association, correspondence, and minutes of annual meetings and executive board meetings.
  - Annual and other meetings 1970-1989 (Box 1)
  - Annual and other meetings 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - By-laws (Box 1)
  - Church and Ministry Committee minutes 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Church and Ministry Committee minutes 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with registrar 1986 (Box 1)
  - Executive Board minutes 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Executive Board minutes 1978-1988 (Box 1)
  - Financial statements 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Greifswald, Germany, partnership with UNA 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter 1982-1988 (Box 1)
  - Restructuring Meetings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1979-1988 (Box 1)
- Grand Traverse Association
  The Grand Traverse Association series has a paper, entitled "One Hundred Years of the Grand Traverse Association," which was read at the 100th Anniversary meeting of the Association at Traverse City by Reverend W.E. Catton. This paper mentions the location of other items concerning the history of the Grand Traverse Association. Also included are membership lists, meeting minutes, financial statements, and records of controversies regarding two member churches.
  - History (Box 1)
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Administration
    - Membership 1964-1976 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting 1941-1946, 1957, 1959, 1962, 1964-1976 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Board Minutes 1972-1976 (Box 1)
    - Church and Ministry Association Committee 1975 (Box 1)
    - Inter-Church Funding Committee 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Meetings 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports 1971, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - 1951-1966 (Box 1)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Church files
      - Eden Church-Beulah, Michigan (Box 1)
      - Buckley-Cornell United Christian Church (Box 1)
- Lake Superior Association
  In the Lake Superior Association series are versions of this Association's constitution and by-laws (1965). The remainder of the series is composed of general administrative records covering the years from 1889 to 1976, financial records from 1927 to 1951, and correspondence.
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Record Books
    - 1889-circa 1900 (Box 1)
      (list of members of Association, tax roll, church clerk)
    - 1901-April 1916 (Box 1)
    - October 1916-1948 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous records
    - 1897, 1908 (Box 2)
    - 1923, 1925, 1939-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967-1976 (Box 2)
  - Financial Records 1927-1951 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1946, 1967 (Box 2)
- Cheboygan Association
  The Cheboygan Association series contains by-laws adopted in 1964 and amended in 1973. There are also two bound volumes recording activities from 1927 to 1973, followed by files containing annual meeting programs, advisory board meeting minutes, ecclesiastical council records, correspondence, and a church information form completed by the First Congregational Church of Alpena, Michigan in 1972.
  - By-laws (Box 2)
  - Membership 1964-1976 (Box 2)
  - Record Books
    - 1927-September 1964 (Box 2)
    - October, 1964-1973 (Box 2)
  - Advisory Board Meetings 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Annual Meeting Programs 1946, 1960, 1969-1970, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Financial records 1906-1949 (Box 2)
  - Financial records 1970, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Ecclesiastical Councils 1945-1972 (Box 2)
  - Ordinations 1946-1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1949-1976 (Box 2)
  - Church Information Form 1972 (Box 2)